In the previous video, we talked about
在上一个视频里 我们讲解了
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
a cost function for the neural network.
神经网络的代价函数
In this video, let's start to talk about an algorithm,
在这个视频里 让我们来说说
for trying to minimize the cost function.
让代价函数最小化的算法
In particular, we'll talk about the back propagation algorithm.
具体来说 我们将主要讲解反向传播算法
Here's the cost function that
这个就是我们上一个视频里写好的
we wrote down in the previous video.
代价函数
What we'd like to do is
我们要做的就是
try to find parameters theta
设法找到参数
to try to minimize j of theta.
使得J(θ)取到最小值
In order to use either gradient descent
为了使用梯度下降法或者
or one of the advance optimization algorithms.
其他某种高级优化算法
What we need to do therefore is
我们需要做的就是
to write code that takes
写好一个可以通过输入 参数 θ
this input the parameters theta
然后计算 J(θ)
and computes j of theta
和这些
and these partial derivative terms.
偏导数项的代码
Remember, that the parameters
记住 这些神经网络里
in the the neural network of these things,
对应的参数
theta superscript l subscript ij,
也就是 θ 上标 (l) 下标 ij 的参数
that's the real number
这些都是实数
and so, these are the partial derivative terms
所以这些都是我们需要计算的
we need to compute.
偏导数项
In order to compute the
为了计算代价函数
cost function j of theta,
J(θ)
we just use this formula up here
我们就是用上面这个公式
and so, what I want to do
所以我们在本节视频里大部分时间
for the most of this video is
想要做的都是
focus on talking about
重点关注
how we can compute these
如何计算这些
partial derivative terms.
偏导数项
Let's start by talking about
我们从只有一个
the case of when we have only
训练样本的情况
one training example,
开始说起
so imagine, if you will that our entire
假设 我们整个训练集
training set comprises only one
只包含一个训练样本
training example which is a pair xy.
也就是实数对
I'm not going to write x1y1
我这里不写成x(1) y(1)
just write this.
就写成这样
Write a one training example
把这一个训练样本记为 (x, y)
as xy and let's tap through
让我们粗看一遍
the sequence of calculations
使用这一个训练样本
we would do with this one training example.
来计算的顺序
The first thing we do is
首先我们
we apply forward propagation in
应用前向传播方法来
order to compute whether a hypotheses
计算一下在给定输入的时候
actually outputs given the input.
假设函数是否会真的输出结果
Concretely, the called the
具体地说 这里的
a(1) is the activation values
a(1) 就是第一层的激励值
of this first layer that was the input there.
也就是输入层在的地方
So, I'm going to set that to x
所以我准备设定他为
and then we're going to compute
然后我们来计算
z(2) equals theta(1) a(1)
z(2) 等于 θ(1) 乘以 a(1)
and a(2) equals g, the sigmoid
然后 a(2) 就等于 g(z(2)) 函数
activation function applied to z(2)
其中g是一个S型激励函数
and this would give us our
这就会计算出第一个
activations for the first middle layer.
隐藏层的激励值
That is for layer two of the network
也就是神经网络的第二层
and we also add those bias terms.
我们还增加这个偏差项
Next we apply 2 more steps
接下来我们再用2次
of this four and propagation
前向传播
to compute a(3) and a(4)
来计算出 a(3) 和 最后的 a(4)
which is also the upwards
同样也就是假设函数
of a hypotheses h of x.
h(x) 的输出
So this is our vectorized implementation of
所以这里我们实现了把前向传播
forward propagation
向量化
and it allows us to compute
这使得我们可以计算
the activation values
神经网络结构里的
for all of the neurons
每一个神经元的
in our neural network.
激励值
Next, in order to compute
接下来
the derivatives, we're going to use
为了计算导数项 我们将
an algorithm called back propagation.
采用一种叫做反向传播(Backpropagation)的算法
The intuition of the back propagation algorithm
反向传播算法从直观上说
is that for each note
就是对每一个结点
we're going to compute the term
我们计算这样一项
delta superscript l subscript j
δ下标 j 上标(l)
that's going to somehow
这就用某种形式
represent the error
代表了第 l 层的第 j 个结点的
of note j in the layer l.
误差
So, recall that
我们还记得
a superscript l subscript j
a 上标 (l) 下标 j
that does the activation of
表示的是第 l 层第 j 个单元的
the j of unit in layer l
激励值
and so, this delta term
所以这个 δ 项
is in some sense
在某种程度上
going to capture our error
就捕捉到了我们
in the activation of that neural duo.
在这个神经节点的激励值的误差
So, how we might wish the activation
所以我们可能希望这个节点的
of that note is slightly different.
激励值稍微不一样
Concretely, taking the example
具体地讲 我们用
neural network that we have
右边这个有四层
on the right which has four layers.
的神经网络结构做例子
And so capital L is equal to 4.
所以这里大写 L 等于4
For each output unit, we're going to compute this delta term.
对于每一个输出单元 我们准备计算δ项
So, delta for the j of unit in the fourth layer is equal to
所以第四层的第j个单元的δ就等于
just the activation of that
这个单元的激励值
unit minus what was
减去训练样本里的
the actual value of 0 in our training example.
真实值0
So, this term here can
所以这一项可以
also be written h of
同样可以写成
x subscript j, right.
h(x) 下标 j
So this delta term is just
所以 δ 这一项就是
the difference between when a
假设输出
hypotheses output and what
和训练集y值
was the value of y
之间的差
in our training set whereas
这里
y subscript j is
y 下标 j 就是
the j of element of the
我们标记训练集里向量
vector value y in our labeled training set.
的第j个元素的值
And by the way, if you
顺便说一句
think of delta a and
如果你把 δ a 和 y 这三个
y as vectors then you can
都看做向量
also take those and come
那么你可以同样这样写
up with a vectorized implementation of
并且得出一个向量化的表达式
it, which is just
也就是
delta 4 gets set as
δ(4)等于
a4 minus y. Where
a(4) 减去 y 这里
here, each of these delta
每一个变量
4 a4 and y, each of
也就是 δ(4) a(4) 和 y
these is a vector whose
都是一个向量
dimension is equal to
并且向量维数等于
the number of output units in our network.
输出单元的数目
So we've now computed the
所以现在我们计算出
era term's delta
网络结构的
4 for our network.
误差项 δ(4)
What we do next is compute
我们下一步就是计算
the delta terms for the earlier layers in our network.
网络中前面几层的误差项 δ
Here's a formula for computing delta
这个就是计算 δ(3) 的公式
3 is delta 3 is equal
δ(3) 等于
to theta 3 transpose times delta 4.
θ(3) 的转置乘以 δ(4)
And this dot times, this
然后这里的点乘
is the element y's multiplication operation
这是我们从 MATLAB 里知道的
that we know from MATLAB.
对 y 元素的乘法操作
So delta 3 transpose delta
所以 θ(3) 转置乘以
4, that's a vector; g prime
δ(4) 这是一个向量
z3 that's also a vector
g'(z(3)) 同样也是一个向量
and so dot times is
所以点乘就是
in element y's multiplication between these two vectors.
两个向量的元素间对应相乘
This term g prime of
其中这一项 g'(z(3))
z3, that formally is actually
其实是对激励函数 g
the derivative of the activation
在输入值为 z(3) 的时候
function g evaluated at
所求的
the input values given by z3.
导数
If you know calculus, you
如果你掌握微积分的话
can try to work it out yourself
你可以试着自己解出来
and see that you can simplify it to the same answer that I get.
然后可以简化得到我这里的结果
But I'll just tell you pragmatically what that means.
但是我只是从实际角度告诉你这是什么意思
What you do to compute this g
你计算这个 g'
prime, these derivative terms is
这个导数项其实是
just a3 dot times1
a(3) 点乘 (1-a(3))
minus A3 where A3
这里a(3)是
is the vector of activations.
激励向量
1 is the vector of
1是以1为元素的向量
ones and A3 is
a(3) 又是
again the activation
一个对那一层的
the vector of activation values for that layer.
激励向量
Next you apply a similar
接下来你应用一个相似的公式
formula to compute delta 2
来计算 δ(2)
where again that can be
同样这里可以利用一个
computed using a similar formula.
相似的公式
Only now it is a2
只是在这里
like so and I
是 a(2)
then prove it here but you
这里我并没有证明
can actually, it's possible to
但是如果你懂微积分的话
prove it if you know calculus
证明是完全可以做到的
that this expression is equal
那么这个表达式从数学上讲
to mathematically, the derivative of
就等于激励函数
the g function of the activation
g函数的偏导数
function, which I'm denoting
这里我用
by g prime. And finally,
g‘来表示
that's it and there is
最后 就到这儿结束了
no delta1 term, because the
这里没有 δ(1) 项 因为
first layer corresponds to the
第一次对应输入层
input layer and that's just the
那只是表示
feature we observed in our
我们在训练集观察到的
training sets, so that doesn't have any error associated with that.
所以不会存在误差
It's not like, you know,
这就是说
we don't really want to try to change those values.
我们是不想改变这些值的
And so we have delta
所以这个例子中我们的 δ 项就只有
terms only for layers 2, 3 and for this example.
第2层和第3层
The name back propagation comes from
反向传播法这个名字
the fact that we start by
源于我们从
computing the delta term for
输出层开始计算
the output layer and then
δ项
we go back a layer and
然后我们返回到上一层
compute the delta terms for the
计算第三隐藏层的
third hidden layer and then we
δ项 接着我们
go back another step to compute
再往前一步来计算
delta 2 and so, we're sort of
δ(2) 所以说
back propagating the errors from
我们是类似于把输出层的误差
the output layer to layer 3
反向传播给了第3层
to their to hence the name back complication.
然后是再传到第二层 这就是反向传播的意思
Finally, the derivation is
最后 这个推导过程是出奇的麻烦的
surprisingly complicated, surprisingly involved but
出奇的复杂
if you just do this few steps
但是如果你按照
steps of computation it is possible
这样几个步骤计算
to prove viral frankly some
就有可能简单直接地完成
what complicated mathematical proof.
复杂的数学证明
It's possible to prove that if
如果你忽略标准化所产生的项
you ignore authorization then the
我们可以证明
partial derivative terms you want
我们要求的偏导数项
are exactly given by the
恰好就等于
activations and these delta terms.
激励函数和这些 δ 项
This is ignoring lambda or
这里我们忽略了 λ
alternatively the regularization
或者说 标准化项
term lambda will
λ 是等于
equal to 0.
We'll fix this detail later
我们将在之后完善这一个
about the regularization term, but
关于正则化项
so by performing back propagation
所以到现在 我们通过
and computing these delta terms,
反向传播 计算这些δ项
you can, you know, pretty
可以非常快速的计算出
quickly compute these partial
所有参数的
derivative terms for all of your parameters.
偏导数项
So this is a lot of detail.
好了 现在讲了很多细节了
Let's take everything and put
现在让我们把所有内容整合在一起
it all together to talk about
然后说说
how to implement back propagation
如何实现反向传播算法
to compute derivatives with respect to your parameters.
来计算关于这些参数的偏导数
And for the case of when
当我们有
we have a large training
一个非常大的训练样本时
set, not just a training
而不是像我们例子里这样的一个训练样本
set of one example, here's what we do.
我们是这样做的
Suppose we have a training
假设我们有
set of m examples like
m 个样本的训练集
that shown here.
正如此处所写
The first thing we're going to do is
我要做的第一件事就是
we're going to set these delta
固定这些
l subscript i j. So this triangular symbol?
带下标 i j 的 Δ
That's actually the capital Greek
这其实是
alphabet delta .
大写的希腊字母 δ
The symbol we had on the previous slide was the lower case delta.
我们之前写的那个是小写
So the triangle is capital delta.
这个三角形是大写的 Δ
We're gonna set this equal to zero
我们将对每一个i
for all values of l i j.
和 j 对应的 Δ 等于0
Eventually, this capital delta
实际上 这些大写 Δij
l i j will be used
会被用来计算
to compute the partial
偏导数项
derivative term, partial derivative
就是 J(θ)
respect to theta l i j of
关于 θ 上标(l) 下标 i j 的
J of theta.
偏导数
So as we'll see in
所以 正如我们接下来看到的
a second, these deltas are going
这些 δ
to be used as accumulators that
会被作为累加项
will slowly add things in
慢慢地增加
order to compute these partial derivatives.
以算出这些偏导数
Next, we're going to loop through our training set.
接下来我们将遍历我们的训练集
So, we'll say for i equals
我们这样写
1 through m and so
写成 For i = 1 to m
for the i iteration, we're
对于第 i 个循环而言
going to working with the training example xi, yi.
我们将取训练样本 (x(i), y(i))
So
所以
the first thing we're going to do
我们要做的第一件事是
is set a1 which is the
设定a(1) 也就是
activations of the input layer,
输入层的激励函数
set that to be equal to
设定它等于 x(i)
xi is the inputs for our
x(i) 是我们第 i 个训练样本的
i training example, and then
输入值
we're going to perform forward propagation to
接下来我们运用正向传播
compute the activations for
来计算第二层的激励值
layer two, layer three and so
然后是第三层 第四层
on up to the final
一直这样
layer, layer capital L. Next,
到最后一层 L层
we're going to use the output
接下来 我们将用
label yi from this
我们这个样本的
specific example we're looking
输出值 y(i)
at to compute the error
来计算这个输出值
term for delta L for the output there.
所对应的误差项 δ(L)
So delta L is what
所以 δ(L) 就是
a hypotheses output minus what
假设输出减去
the target label was?
目标输出
And then we're going to use
接下来 我们将
the back propagation algorithm to
运用反向传播算法
compute delta L minus 1,
来计算 δ(L-1)
delta L minus 2, and
δ(L-2)
so on down to delta 2 and once again
一直这样直到 δ(2)
there is now delta 1 because
再强调一下 这里没有 δ(1)
we don't associate an error term with the input layer.
因为我们不需要对输入层考虑误差项
And finally, we're going to
最后我们将用
use these capital delta terms
这些大写的 Δ
to accumulate these partial derivative
来累积我们在前面写好的
terms that we wrote down on the previous line.
偏导数项
And by the way, if you
顺便说一下
look at this expression, it's possible to vectorize this too.
如果你再看下这个表达式 你可以把它写成向量形式
Concretely, if you think
具体地说
of delta ij as
如果你把
a matrix, indexed by subscript ij.
δij 看作一个矩阵 i j代表矩阵中的位置
Then, if delta L is
那么 如果 δ(L) 是一个矩阵
a matrix we can rewrite
我们就可以写成
this as delta L, gets
Δ(l) 等于
updated as delta L plus
Δ(l) 加上
lower case delta L plus
小写的 δ(l+1)
one times aL transpose.
乘以 a(l) 的转置
So that's a vectorized implementation of
这就是用向量化的形式
this that automatically does
实现了对所有 i 和 j
an update for all values of
的自动更新值
i and j. Finally, after
最后
executing the body of
执行这个 for 循环体之后
the four-loop we then go outside the four-loop
我们跳出这个 for 循环
and we compute the following.
然后计算下面这些式子
We compute capital D as
我们按照如下公式计算
follows and we have
大写
two separate cases for j
我们对于 j=0 和 j≠0
equals zero and j not equals zero.
分两种情况讨论
The case of j equals zero
在 j=0 的情况下
corresponds to the bias
对应偏差项
term so when j equals
所以当 j=0 的时候
zero that's why we're missing
这就是为什么
is an extra regularization term.
我们没有写额外的标准化项
Finally, while the formal proof
最后 尽管严格的证明对于
is pretty complicated what you
你来说太复杂
can show is that once
你现在可以说明的是
you've computed these D terms,
一旦你计算出来了这些
that is exactly the partial
这就正好是
derivative of the cost
代价函数关于
function with respect to each
每一个参数的偏导数
of your perimeters and so you
所以你可以把他们用在
can use those in either gradient
梯度下降法
descent or in one of the advanced authorization
或者其他一种更高级的
algorithms.
优化算法上
So that's the back propagation
这就是反向传播算法
algorithm and how you compute
以及你如何计算
derivatives of your cost
神经网络代价函数的
function for a neural network.
偏导数
I know this looks like this
我知道这个里面
was a lot of details and this was a lot of steps strung together.
细节琐碎 步骤繁多
But both in the programming
但是在后面的编程作业
assignments write out and later
和后续的视频里
in this video, we'll give
我都会给你一个
you a summary of this so
清晰的总结
we can have all the pieces
这样我们就可以把算法的所有细节
of the algorithm together so that
拼合到一起
you know exactly what you need
这样 当你想运用反向传播算法
to implement if you want
来计算你的神经网络的代价函数
to implement back propagation to compute
关于这些参数的偏导数的时候
the derivatives of your neural network's
你就会清晰地知道
cost function with respect to those parameters.
你要的是什么